So what is debiasing, and why is it so important
when defining a problem?
So debiasing is taking a very structured approach
to think about what are some of the biases that may come into
the way we define a problem up front,
and think about what we can do as problem-solving leaders
to try to take that bias out of the situation.
Everyone has biases.
It's interesting — we often think that others have biases,
but we ourselves don't.
And it's interesting that when you do problem solving in the moment,
your biases are not always at the forefront of your thinking.
Put differently, biases are actually oftentimes good, right?
Because they're heuristics — they're human heuristics.
They're shortcuts, so that we know when a lion is running towards us,
we don't have to actively problem-solve.
We understand that, hey, the shortcut is: we've got to run.
So biases are intrinsically there to protect us.
However, we actually need to be aware of them as business leaders
to really make sure that we're not reconfirming something
that has historically happened but may not happen again.
So what I often find very common in a lot of problem solving
is that we actually have
confirmation bias: we're all actually looking just to confirm
whatever finding or thought that we had before.
Or we have groupthink — because the leader thinks something,
therefore it must be right, and we all just kind of fall in line.
The most effective way for us to actually try and debias a bit
is to sometimes have a challenger session —
your organisation might call it something different.
It's to actually take whoever is a strong leader
or a voice in one perspective,
and see if they can argue the other perspective. And vice versa.
It's sometimes a little bit funny. It can feel a little bit contrived.
But it's an incredibly powerful way for us to make sure
that we're actually checking our blind spots,
and that we're actually challenging ourselves also to be
a bit more empathetic as leaders in our problem solving —
so that we're not so grounded and married in our own perspectives
that we can't actually see what our counterparts might be thinking.